so this is the uh some utility Kaya
chapter 22 verse 85 this is called
yarmaka which is a
which is a
biku yamaka and it's in reference to his
wrong view that he was holding
which was
he was going around saying a beaker
whose defilements have ended and arahant
at the breakup of the body
he ceases is destroyed and is not is not
or does not exist Beyond or after death
so there's many such uh wrong views okay
so why is he wrong
to state that he does not exist after
death
because it states what's after that um
um
well after the breakup of the areas
so it's wrong simply because it's
implying after
note that that you know what's after so
that is this after oh no he might not
maybe he knows maybe he doesn't
obviously he doesn't know but the thing
is
it seems according to the sutta that
even the statement is wrong regardless
of whether it's whether he knows or not
so why is it even wrong to state
that he's he does not exist after death
can you not state it can you just
is it okay to think for yourself as to
what happens to other hunt after death
why is why are those the problem
why any view is pertaining to such
thoughts would be a problem
because of that which they are
pertaining to the arah hunt he does not
exist after death as though he gets
destroyed but even theoretically say if
they are not necessarily implying the
sense of self if somebody's just trying
to figure out what data Hunt is or would
be
would these thoughts still be wrong
um
and if so then why
if somebody is just trying to
if somebody is trying to figure
basically the only way to understand
what an arrow hand is is
to because
because
basically so then somebody who is comes
and asks another hunt what happens after
death or rather says also arahandan doesn't
or rather says also arahandan doesn't
exist after death or exists after death
or both doesn't exist and neither exists
after death
why any of such statement would be wrong
is it because other hand exists after
that so he doesn't or neither or both
yeah wrong in a sense that it doesn't matter
wrong in a sense that it doesn't matter
it says like yeah exactly well it's
wrong basically not because of what
other hand is or isn't it's wrong
because the threshold of the question
implies existence so whether there is
arahunt or not or whatever else for that
person on the basis of that view in the
question they see nothing below
existence of upadhana they see nothing
below that in terms of question in and
of itself is based on upadhana it's
based on that which arahan isn't
doesn't have
so that's why there is no right answer
to it because it's entirely top to
bottom a question based on a wrong
assumption so is isn't both is and isn't neither is
so is isn't both is and isn't neither is
nor isn't still focuses on the content
of my answer and completely no
self-awareness in regard to the question
that that question presupposes already
existence Baba which arahunt is free
from the basis of the question is wrong
completely completely cannot have a
right answer it cannot have a right
answer because it's a completely wrong
question any answer given to it
uh it would just basically then
maybe inadvertently
but it would still be um affirming the
the wrong the wrong base of a question
so
if somebody wants to then understand
what jarahunt what happens to another
hunt after the body breaks apart well
the only way to understand that is to
remove every Slide the slightest traces
of Bava in your mind in your Notions
from the five Aggregates basically
and then obviously you wouldn't be
asking that question because you got
your answer
in other words you cannot approach it
you cannot understand it you cannot see
it through an external standpoint an
answer to such questions would be
affirmation of the external standpoint
to that situation
and that's impossible even so see like
even so the party is impossible through
the external standpoint
but through the various right external
through the various right external
standpoints you can narrow it down and
then discern it internally but as you
progress further to the power in the
path and coming like to the point of
that there is simply no room for any
external standpoint even the right one
and that's why arhand is himself Beyond
The Right View as well
so then exactly like in the other
suitors if a question were to pertain to also
if a question were to pertain to also
what happens then in iban or after
nibana or parinibana it makes no sense
the question makes no sense because
the the lowest that question can go
it's still too much of Baba for any
right answer to apply so to speak
so you need to undo undo the existence
of it the the Assumption of existence in
it
but then as I said then you would get
the answer by undoing the question not
by providing an answer to the question
so just to mention some other views
similar
self is neither suffering or happy and
is unafflicted after death unafflicted
so basically it's independent of
feelings and everything that comes and
goes and then I think so why is everyone yeah
it assumes an actual temporal self yeah
yeah but practically speaking like say
somebody's like well I don't know what
extra temporal mean it just that's how
it feels for me myself is not affected
by pain or pleasure and thus it will
remain unaffected is there a way that
somebody who holds their wrong view can
verify for themselves without just
accepting your view now over extra
temporal self-explanation can I see a
contradiction a discrepancy in the very
view I'm holding that can then show me
that you are right
I am in control of the things that make
up your sense of self so feelings yeah
so it's basically one base would be the
the lack of control another thing would
be okay you might have Notions about
yourself not being affected but can you
even conceive yourself your sense of
self apart from any feeling have you
ever conceived it that you have not felt
something oh no so it's it's an absolute
fantasy even right here right now as I'm
thinking it I'm feeling something
can I even imagine exactly a thought of
sense of self without a feeling well
that's inconceivable so my view is truly
inconceivable here while I'm stating it
and and on the base of that if somebody
ever honest they could see that as a
obviously insurmountable contradiction
and they would have to then give up that
view and that's kind of the only way you can
and that's kind of the only way you can
really of course if somebody's more
authentic than the others you know they
will need less instruction less
convincing but fundamentally the only way to really
but fundamentally the only way to really
approve the wrong view or wrong views of
all sorts of Kinds is to show
to personally hold it if they're
authentic enough to show them that in
and of itself it's a contradiction in
terms then not simply by offering another
then not simply by offering another
better view because then they might even
take your view then but they're still
taking it wrongly
they're still done well they don't know
if it's if it's right for themselves
they just took it because it sounds
better now
but you really want them to know that
it's right in and of itself because it's
a trick from contradiction free from
anything that you would not be able to
verify Here and Now for yourself as okay
this there's no discrepancy this adds up
this doesn't add up and so on
so in this particular case it's
impossible it was impossible it's just
it was impossible it's just
inconceivable
despite how it feels how your sense of
self feels it's inconceivable to even
imagine because that imagination is
underlined by something you're currently
feeling so you saying the tentative is
so you saying the tentative is
independent of good or bad feeling
whatever comes this way simply does not
actually match even your own experience
of that sense of self which is always
always paired with feeling with
perception and that pleasing thought that fantasy
and that pleasing thought that fantasy
that image of that sense of self
independent of all these things
there's feeling underneath that as well
while you're saying it
and if you're honest you'll see it and
you realize well then it cannot be
independent regardless of how much
it appears to be so it only appears to
be so because you've been cultivating
such assumptions
well how much we want it to be so all
right yeah yeah how much you want it
then
and in another suit it gives a few other
examples self exists for me
this is true and certain that's that's
for sure
no self-exists for me I perceive self
with self I perceive not selfless self I
perceive self but not self it is this
self of mine that I speak that speaks
and feels and experiences
the result of good and bad actions but
the self of mind is permanent
Everlasting Eternal not subject to
change and it will endure as long as
eternity yeah
what's the problem with that so self
exists for me self doesn't exist for me
to have both have neither what's the
problem with that statement
well the few problems but let's come up
with some
yeah again the basis of any of those
statements is already
a statement about
assuming self basically or taking the
taking self as a saying
exists for me
self doesn't exist self-bots and other
means that exists for you exactly and
the main problem with this view is that
that's where the self actually is it's
on the level of existence not on the
level where you say itself is so self
exists for me no self exists for me
either way no self exists for you
because of your statement of existence
whether that statement of existence is
then referred to the sense of self for
both or neither that's irrelevant that's
already the secondary result
of or self very much exists because
things exist in that Bava sense
existence is the self that already
exists for you when you say that that
self over there exists for me
so it's simply not where the sense of
self is and you're overlooking it
because it's on the basis of existence
and that's why it comes down to then
exactly like oh with
with self he perceives self I with
existence he perceived what he thinks
self is which is then double self
with self he perceives not self but
again still his experience is rooted in
oneself or then he would if he put the
emphasis on that what he thinks self is
then would not exist with like a knock
self in a way he can be perceiving
either way there will have to be a
reference point of self
either here or there or both because
it's in both it's in existing of the
self is already the self
plus the self that you now assumed even
further to exist so whether you in other
words that's for me like whether you
deny or affirm the sense of self you
still very much hold the sense of self
because you very much hold the existence
even if you don't Define it as a sense
of self it will be yourself
that's why exactly when they did
sometimes ask the Buddha also Master
Gautama says there is no self
there is no self the normal self exists
so either way the root the basis of the
self-view the existence the bhava remain
would remain completely unchanged uh
regardless of what answer the master
master gotama would give them so he
would not say anything he would just
remain quiet
because it's a completely wrong
assumption wrong question
which then they would take as the the
right answer
so it's simply
to loaded question basically question
loaded with existence so you cannot
answer it correctly without dismantling
the existence but that's not what the
question pertains to
so then yeah
so a lot of these views are followed by
this kind of statement
having such a view
one is one is in a jungle of views which
is difficult to pass through and leaves
one wriggling swaying in this way in
that struggling and fettered so you're
just going from there's no end to those
yeah just keep getting entertain
where you twist it
so back to biku yamaka and his view
about the arahunt not existing after
death so other beakers try to persuade him
so other beakers try to persuade him
otherwise but he he didn't want to
abandon that view
and said Venable saripota came
and asked him some questions
so in the evening the Venable sari puta
approached the Venable yamaka and asked
him what do you think
so he's not he's not answering he's not
saying if the other hand exists or not
he's just asking him questions
what do you think his form permanent or
impermanent impermanence sir but if it's impermanent
impermanence sir but if it's impermanent
is it suffering or happiness suffering
since its impermanent suffering and
subject to change is it fit to be
regarded thus this is mine I am this
this is myself it says no
so likewise with the other Aggregates
feeling perception
tensions Consciousness so okay let's
stop there now
um
they're not going to answer the
questions that big cuyama caused
he's going to go and question him about
the validity of his questions
which is what we've been saying
so why wouldn't he bring the five
Aggregates why would he talk about that
in light of what we just said
why would that be the right way to go
about these questions
as I said before the the
so
he's not giving an explanation
um he's he's
inviting him to discern in his presently
enjoying experience
the nature of this sense of self that
he's referring or that he's implying in
his question so
um but yeah so but why would then why
would he talk about a form and feeling
Daniels why would you talk about if I
were presently enjoying the experience
um
yeah do you have control over yeah form
or so so
um
yeah like the fact that you will die for
example or the your you know you don't
have any control over right but he
wasn't talking about death though he was
talking about what but what's there
living the five aggregates
or somebody who has the view could say
well yeah I don't I don't control form
feeling none of that but my sense itself
is independent of these things
so
but um how do then how did you then
dislodge
of the independency applies permanency
so two so two so there's two things
involved the identification with the
aggregates and regarding that itself which which is
and regarding that itself which which is
Possible only because those Aggregates
are regarded as permanence so to then
question the Aggregates and explicitly
do you see that as impermanent and he
says yes they are impermanence they're
being that the only thing that is being
those five Aggregates if all that's in
permanent then that independency cannot
stand exactly it's but what we said in
regard to the that view of self and the
feeling yeah you start questioning
Aggregates because again you would point
out to that person that well as
independent as it might feel
as concerned about what's after you
might be can you experience that concern
that independence of self or whatever
without feeling without this feeling
underneath it without this form
without its intention inconceivable like
even in your imagination the utmost
Eternal Atman projected sense of self
ever enduring again as the Buddha said
cannot be apart from The Sixth Sense
base if somebody claims I'll show you
the all apart from this that's simply
not factually possible
so it would have to be on the basis of
this and what is the basis of this oh
it's the form
it's the feeling is the perception
intention and then
if now a person is clear that regardless
of what view they have that view is
simultaneously always paired with this
with the five Aggregates or one of them
whichever way you you you would have
emphasized it so then by questioning the
basis of the five Aggregates you realize
that oh well it's inconceivable for this
to be apart from it it's inconceivable
for this to exist independently
any notion of existence independent
existence of the five Aggregates is
exactly it's based on this notion of
ignoring the fact that it cannot be
apart from the five Aggregates and it
cannot be apart from that which is
Thoroughly top to bottom impermanent
subject to change unownable unpleasant
then it cannot be taken as mine as an
independent self that can exist apart
from this and exactly what I was asking
now is because I'm sure many people
would have read the suit and read the
suit is like oh you see these views but
then it seems almost like a leap oh now
you just aggregate okay but it's like
with the connection between the two like
because if you were to really understand
this the way the sarikuta was asking him
you would then be free from any notion
of an external sense of self or conceit
so but if you think you're understanding
the questioning on Aggregates while
still have your sense of self-intact
then you are missing something and
that's what I'm pointing out you're
missing that connection that sort of uh
clear reasoning that has been pushed
far enough whereby you cannot now ignore
the fact that doesn't matter how lofty
how remote how independent how Eternal
how permanent your sense of self might
feel in regard to this or that that in
and of itself is still another
experience as a whole that it's
experience of the five aggregates
so by re-including it in that which it
cannot be outside of
such Reflections about impermanence of
Aggregates begin to apply
begin to actually undermine your sense
of self or that existence of that
question that implies existence
yeah and he goes on to say
to yarmaker so you should see any kind
of form
or the 500 gets any kind of aggregate
past future present internal external
course of fine inferior or Superior far
only Aggregates with right understanding this
Aggregates with right understanding this
is not mine I am not this this is not
myself and seeing this a a noble disciple grows
and seeing this a a noble disciple grows
disenchanted with the aggregates
being disenchanted desire Fades away
when desire Fades away they are freed
liberated when they are free they know
they are freed they then understand
birth is ended the whole life has been
completed what has to be done has been
done there is no returning to any state
of existence
so and he continues to question yarmaka
do you regard form as the tatagata
form as the arahunt it says no do you
regard feeling perceptions intentions
conscience as the arohans no
what do you think do you regard the
arrow hunt as inform or outside form in
feeling or outside feeling in perception outside
or outside feeling in perception outside
in the attention in Consciousness
outside of consciousness
do you regard
form feeling perceptions intentions
what's the problem with in
you can say like okay I don't regard it
outside of the Aggregates but it's in
them why is that wrong as well
because it implies an outside yeah
exactly because you place it inside and
the only way you can play something
inside is by assuming it being separated
from it first
I outside of it
so
he continues the question what do you
think do you regard form feeling
perceptions intentions Consciousness
taken together
as the other hand as the South the whole
thing yeah that's that's the song
they individually cannot be it's a group
they're gonna be either comprise the
five heaps did remain the same unchanged
regardless of whether together alone
says do you think uh the arohans is one who
do you think uh the arohans is one who
is or the selfish one with who is
without the Aggregates yeah again those
the Aggregates yeah again those
independent separation yeah
know you
but friend we're not finding that the
view of the tatagata thing or the self
is true or definite
it or
we're not finding that the view of self
is
true definite independent thing is it
fitting for you to declare its
independence and truthfulness
yeah that's exactly what we said just in
regard to that self and feeling
like if he's honestly stop daily as well
regardless of how lofty might feel
exactly there is still feeling pressure
can I even conceive any notion the
slightest notion of I am or the self
without feeling being there impossible so I must
feeling being there impossible so I must
not ignore that context that it's
whenever I think about the sense of self
and the great self and the big self and
the higher self and myself but in fear
yourself past self future self far self
all I'm thinking
is exactly thoughts that are five
Aggregates that have sure certain valued
content of the independence which is a
contradiction in terms fundamentally all
I'm thinking is an image is a feeling
there's an intention it's the form it's
a thought it's basically the five
hundreds so that's how you can't just
stop thinking the sense of self but you
can actually expand the context in
regard to the thought of the sense of
self and one would be expanding that context
and one would be expanding that context
rightly if one does not double down and
blindly commit to the view that pertains
to that already wrongly assumed external
sense of self
because that person will not be
establishing the context because they
have set themselves in external view
that my sense of self is independent of
all of this and its Eternal Everlasting
and even if you don't think in such
course terms do you think simply that
everything will work out forever after
do you have any implication that
whatever you're doing is just heading up
well that's already an external point of
view that you assumed in a sense of oh
everything would be fine regardless of
whether it is pleasure or pain
experienced Here and Now
but that thought of after of the
external of you know Independence and
safety how can they be safe when the only way
how can they be safe when the only way
you can know it is on account of this
five Aggregates that are very unsafe so
to speak
so if you were honest you realize that
your idea of the highest
heaven and deity well
might be good but in and of itself it's
still within this which is not in my
control which is subject to change thus
this too
will have to change them so it cannot be
the Eternal safety because the notion of
Eternity exists on an account of these
non-eternal five aggregates
and that's the
both at the same time and to see the
nature of it also as in like you can
have a
you can it's very obvious let's say
I can think about I can think about
feeling being impermanent I can say oh
well that can't be myself I can't be
feeling but then at the same time to see
that that everything else is dependent
or within cannot be without feeling yeah
is you could or you can sort of see that
one but that said but at the same time
to see that the feeling being
impermanent totally undermined that's
why you would always go through these
five because you might not be taking the
feeling at the time when you're looking
at the feeling means you're taking some
other aggregate you know all other
Aggregates you know just see that this
thought that feeling is impermanent is
still undermined by the feeling yeah
yeah even on that level but you say
sometimes just whatever for whatever
reason your sense of self is just
wiggling out of the feeling and it just
doesn't feel like feeling is yours well
can you know that sense of self it's not
perceived no ah so then what perception
is yours no it's not uh so that matter
then what shape and form my assumption
of sense of self can assume it's going
to be one or all of the five of the
Aggregates are one among them cannot be
outside of them just inconceivable
because if it were truly independent of
the firecrity would be independent of
designation independent independent of of of of an
independent independent of of of of an
image independent of being known
independent of being conscious of it
will not exist basically
you will not be able to talk about it
and then the bakery armica he finally
changes his mind
this is a
he's abandoned that view and then
somebody put asks him
so
if others were to ask you
when a baker is in our hunt whose taints
are destroyed what happens to him with
the breakup of the body after death how
would you answer
he says if they were to ask me that I
would answer friends
the agric form is impermanent what is
impermanence is suffering what is
suffering has ceased and passed away
same with feeling perceptions intentious
consciousness there's a
there's a
it would not if somebody was asking he
would not give them an answer that
pertains to that question but he would
actually show that the question
inevitably is rooted in a contradiction
of ownership impermanence in regards to
the five aggregates
so yamaka became one of the Noble on
Tuesday yeah yeah
he no longer assuming yeah no longer
being able to assume that no the
external Independence in regard to sense
of self whether he projected into the
Buddha and other hand or others doesn't
matter doesn't have the usual stock
phrases that are sometimes connected
with like
for him to come up with that kind of
answer yeah well I think maybe it
doesn't have the usual phrases because
he might not have been completely like a
suitabad he might have kind of you know
uh understood because he obviously was
able to understand the questioning in
regards to the Aggregates which means he
was fairly familiar with that he was
just probably an oversight on his part
fell into view and then just tried to
for whatever reason argue the point from
the assumed view ignoring what he kind
of voted and knew in a way yeah
and when was saripota says good
and then
says he will make up a simile for him in
order to convey the same meaning even
more clearly
says Suppose there was a householder a
rich man with much wealth and property
protected by a bodyguard
then some man would appear who wanted to
ruin him to harm him to take his life
it would occur to that man this
householder is a rich man with much
wealth and property protected by a
bodyguard it won't be easy to take his life by
it won't be easy to take his life by
force let me get close to him and then
take his life
he would then approach that householder
and say I would like to serve you sir
then that household it would appoint him
as a servant
the man would serve him rising up before
before him retire retiring after him
doing whatever he wants agreeable in his
conduct endearing in his speech and that
householder would consider him a friend
a best friend and he would place trust
in him but when that when the man
becomes aware that the householder was
has placed trust in him then finding
finding him alone he would take his life
with a sharp knife
so what do you think when that man had
approached that householder and said to
him I would serve you sir wasn't he a
murderer even then though the other did
not recognize him as my murderer
and when the man was serving him rising
up before him retiring after him doing
whatever he want at once agreeable in
his conduct endearing in his speech
wasn't he a murderer then too though the
other did not recognize him as my
murderer and when the Man Came Upon him
while he was alone and took his life
with a sharp knife
wasn't he a murderer then too though the
other did not recognize him as my
murderer says yes friend likewise the ordinary
says yes friend likewise the ordinary
person who is not uh does not see the
noble ones who is not skilled in their
discipline and Dharma
regards form as self or selfish possessing form
form as self or selfish possessing form
or form as in self or self as inform
he does not understand as it really is
impermanent Aggregates as impermanent
Aggregates or
painful Aggregates as painful so he
plays his trust in them he turns a blind
eye to the nature of them he doesn't
understand murderous Aggregates as
murderous aggregates
and he becomes engaged with him clings
to them and takes a stand upon them as
myself and why why is the simile
fitting what is supposed to say let me
give you something a little then further
hammering what he said
why is the uh why is the simile of a
somebody becoming your friend
and then killing you
why is that more fitting than simply
saying yeah you know that which is yours
will kill you type of thing
because it pertains to why you
say deceived by the or you don't see the
nature of the Aggregates it's not
because they're just sort of inherently
kind of ineffably deceptive or something
it's because they're pleasing held dear
like agreeable
um and allow you into safety like this
body just I mean just for the body for
example is the most obvious one
like when does the when he talks about
like the intoxication of Youth and
health and everything it gives and where
does that intoxication
where does that take place I suppose
is that on the level of
views ideas
no or it's on the internal level on the
Eternal relationship
what the latter yes and that's kind of
the point so as we were saying the whole
the nature of any self view is assuming
that independent separation being it
external to all of this so if somebody
just comes on that level
and tells you how all of that is is for
your harm as many people would have read
this but not approve to the sense of
self many people would have understood
the simile to some extent but not the
brutal sense of self why is that well
because he and that's the point of the
simile that can be easily overlooked is
it's not just a question of oh he's a
murderer by the way the question is he
kills you from by entering you in like
from internally basically he approaches
you through that internal part that you
don't see because all you see is oh I'm
over there this is mine I'm projected
I'm projected but he sort of sneaks past
all of that so that's what somebody
would you know everybody who starts
would have these external Notions
externally projected a student sends
himself independent of the five
aggregates so if they were to uproot that they need
so if they were to uproot that they need
to first see how these Aggregates are
first that friend and then within that
friendship discern their murderous
intent they can't just externally hear
about the murderous intent because
they'll take that another thing with
their sense of self external and they
won't feel a fact they won't feel
threatened like I won't feel threatened if I see an
like I won't feel threatened if I see an
external murderer over there outside of
my home outside of my kingdom but if
suddenly I recognize that somebody who's
been my closest friend Confidant for
last 50 years or he is the murderer's
intent oh now I cannot remain
indifferent to that because of my trust
I placed in him
not because he suddenly became a
murderer and he wasn't before
and that trust is that always that
internal oversight always happens
internally when you assume you sense
yourself externally and that's the
problem like this these things are that
they're so close like the simulator
doesn't even it cannot even convey just
how close yes friend is you can keep
telling to yourself as a mantra that
this is all you know harmful and
impermanent and that's exactly what you
said like a person would not even know
where to look for the Aggregates because
when they contemplate the Aggregates
that's not what they Aggregates are
that's already the result of them having
taken up the aggregates so and that same
as we said so many times before you want
to contemplate Anita
you can't just oh yeah see that's
impermanent that's in this car but this
is impermanent that's impermanent it's
irrelevant oh look he's a murderer none
of that makes no diff no let me find
first things that are my friend that I
hold dearly that I'm pretty much
attached to that I would not be able to
remain indifferent if they change and
let me contemplate them as impermanent
as a threat as a trap so what are those
things for people
what would be the most obvious
things family exactly
children spouses relatives
spouses relatives
what what another what's another thing
in anybody
the body your own body health health
exactly intoxication with health youth
strength what other thing on the level
of the rotation reputation yeah that's
the images itself but wealth
uh savings safety of your home
safety of your situation like physical
kind of safety like Comfort all of those
things you realize are taking for
granted because
because
well it's kind of I don't think it would
be very hard for people it's like you
just even have an inkling to against
these things it would be already
too frightening because most of them
people's concern
are directed towards then keeping your
mind away from thinking these bad
thoughts in regard to things that are
dear to you but
how can those stores be bad if they're
effectual or because they can be bad but that
or because they can be bad but that
means the facts are bad
the facts are subjected to sickness
aging and death so yeah that is bad but
why is that bad is is it a problem that
this person who pretended to be my
friend was a murderer is that my problem why is
was a murderer is that my problem why is
that my problem
when does it become my problem that he
wants to kill me
when you Delight in that friendship when
you left him in the house exactly when
you take him as a friend when you don't
discern his motives but if you don't do
any of that his murderous intent is not
your problem it cannot murder you
because he hasn't gained your confidence
your trust
but again you can't
the the situation you find yourself in you
the situation you find yourself in you
can't not let him in because he's in
yeah we're talking yeah we're talking
like in on the level of theory so people
can wrap their head around but yeah you
don't start in a neutral position you
already start with well five closest
friends and they're all here competing
who's going to kill you first
and you don't even see it you you still
plan further engage further
on account of their friendship and
you're actually becoming even more
dependent on their presence yet their
entire purpose of their presence is to
take you out
so I was thinking just
um
in relation to the
it's not necessarily so easy to see the
things that are so close
um for example family like you can think
about doesn't know your mother or something
doesn't know your mother or something
that is in dear to you and like if she
dies when people's family of a close
family die you might feel grief
but what it doesn't usually occur to you
is that even the grief on account of
your mother dying and the thoughts of
like that she's still
even she's dead she's my mother my
mother is dead but that's
is in a way even more dear
and it's not because you know
whether she's alive or she's dead she is
still dear as my mother as like
something that makes me who I am so yeah
so how'd you then approve that
yeah
like that that even and what is the end
of that
let's stop thinking it would that be an
end of it no it's it's as in like that
you could lose even that
like that that memory for example or
that because even that can change how
would you lose their memory Alzheimer's
but why would then you won't suffering
account of it if you don't remember it
so Alzheimer's is pretty scary you know
we're scary when you don't have it
when you have it you've lost perspective
on it yeah but that doesn't I mean you
could say the same for like oh well I
you know for death you know like death
yeah that's exactly what people say
that's exactly so why how hot like
because it's obviously they're not
enough if they just because that's
exactly what they would fall into well
I will die when I die out that's fine
why why scare myself with it now
that is a sort of historic position in
life and death cannot be there together
so when I'm dead I'm dead so why worry
about it when I'm alive and so you show
them so why worry about it yeah
why why should you worry about it why
should you worry about exactly even that
oh my mother has passed away still dear
to me oh why is that then
still a problem that thought
why why should I worry about why should
I think about death
if it's not here yet then when it's here
well then I can't do anything about it
huh so why why why is it beneficial
so why why why is it beneficial
like we saw because we're Buddhist well
put that aside but why is it beneficial
factually it is beneficial to think
about it and what would then the benefit
be why is it beneficial why you should
think about it
results in well
why is it not beneficial to say well
I'll die when I die in the meantime I
won't think about it because you're
still suffering account because that's
not what that is what you think that is
what you think losing the loved one is
isn't it's based on your already being
it's based on your already being
intoxicated already having the ownership
so when you think about death
you might feel initially that but even
that takes effort to sustain that
initial anxiety in the face of it and if
you're not careful you would just fall
onto another view external view our
death will come to this
you don't feel affected factually
because you already projected yourself
externally you you're not seeing it on
that internal intimate level of my
friendship so
so
and that's exactly what people would
because it's unavoidable for them to
think or experience losing their loved
ones yet most of them still don't turn
to Dharma why is that well because the
grief that you cope with it by assuming
another external point of view to it
but if you were honest even then you
recommended well
see the problem of me
not thinking about that is because first
and foremost do I even know what death
is and to what extent I understand that
to what extent I've just projected
another idea onto it and secondly if I
think I will be unmoved by Death
whenever it comes or it won't be a
bigger problem
surely then I shouldn't be moved by
anything else that's inferior to that
death all these little well he said this
she said that yet I'm very moved by
those things I do get annoyed I get
lustful I get full desire I get full of
anger but somehow
but somehow
the utmost you know bad experience of
dying disintegrating pain falling apart
but I will be unmoved in regard to that
is that a realistic expectation if I'm
moved on a kind of sight on smell taste
touches surely I will be moved when those organs
surely I will be moved when those organs
that provide me with Titans multi
starches are actually breaking apart and I'm
are actually breaking apart and I'm
witnessing that
so it's like okay so first and foremost
I'm probably have a very inaccurate idea
of what death is
um and then secondly exactly I still
suffer Here and Now
so I can keep turning a blind eye to it
like your relative passes you grieve
and then you stop grieving why is that
could you why did you suffer in the
first place
because you don't suffer when somebody
else passes that's irrelevant to you
so why did you suffer in the first place
because it was your relative yeah so
yeah it was basically your thing was
subjected to change that you didn't want
and why don't you suffer now is it
because you removed the ownership of
these things because you obviously
didn't because you still think of it my
relative my mother but why don't you
suffer now
is it because you understood it or
because you just buried it again with
the distraction of the sense objects and
sense organs and pleasure you get
through it
so and that's exactly why people then
who have lost their loved ones
cope with it dealt with it continue with
their life well if they were to then go
say on a retreat or a more secluded
environment withdrawn from sense objects
and distractions and Pleasures all those
previously coped things will come back
completely unresolved and not just
passing away anything unpleasant you
experienced goes out in light of mine as
the Buddha said so many times has no
other means of dealing with pain other
than engaging with sensuality and
bearing it under the pain you bury down
there pleasure pleasure Perpetual but
then the more you do it the more you
dependent on that pleasure that's
ordered it
quite burdening and hard to access or
hard to sustain and so on so that's
that's kind of the point you recognize
that well wait why did I suffer in the
first place sure I don't suffer anymore
I dealt with it she's gone it's fine no
but why did I suffer in the first place
if I suffered on account of that in the
first place can I suffer on kind of
other things and then what well then
I'll have to deal with it so then I'll
be burdened with having to cope manage
but is it possible to not suffer in the
first place is it possible to not even
be touched by that suffering so I have
nothing to deal with and that's the true
Freedom there is no debt I had to pay
back then
or work off
and yeah if you're then honest you
recognize okay so you didn't really
suffer because this form changed mother
passed away or something you suffered
because you were taking that which
cannot be yours is yours
okay so am I still doing that in regard
to other things oh hell yeah
which means when those things change I
will then suffer if not the same maybe
probably even more because see if an
external form was dear to you imagine
how much more your own form your own
organs that you use to get the pleasure
and distraction and so on to experience
all these other secondary things well
that's even more dear to you so imagine
how much more you will suffer then
but again not because those things that
are subject to change would change but
because those things that are subject to
change well you take up is yours by
ignoring that they're subject to change
by turning a blind eye to engaging
through sensuality and distraction
that's it
so death is presently enduring it's not
something in the future but in order for
that to be understood really that the weight
to be understood really that the weight
of that person first needs to well again
to some honest you recognize okay so the
ownership taking up things is there
that's the root of suffering I should
really aim to not to be free from
suffering because if they don't do that
then they just adopt another external
view in regard to death and death won't
apply to them and that's why I mentioned
what I did in regard to that simulation
it's like she said oh yeah it's a murder
yes I'll be murdered I'm fine no no you
gotta recognize that that person who is
saying I'll be you yourself those
Aggregates those perceptions that's
already there murdering you so your
thought of you'll be fine is another
trap that will murder you
it's not you you have no external
standpoint which is always assumed by saying oh
which is always assumed by saying oh
well when death comes that's it oh so
basically you kind of imply to your own
Assumption of existence of the external
standpoint that you won't be affected by
it
and that's fine you cannot get rid of
that notion but then you start including
that notion okay so when I say death
will come whenever it comes I'll deal
with it then
and I feel safe on account of that
thought here and now oh but that is
another five Aggregates here and now
that I'm taking a safe
on account of admitting that their root
of complete known safety
so if you're honest and just push the
same Principle as far as it goes you'll
realize okay yeah all of this that I
know is that murderer that pretends to
be my friend form feelings perceptions
intentions awareness Consciousness
that's it all of it
all of it is the friend
all of it is the murderer that pretends
to be my friend and allows me into sense
of safety by saying oh no death will
come to everyone you know no problem by
providing me with his external self uh
external Notions of self views wrong
views in regard to the Aggregates and
everything else so that I don't see him
for what it is
making you believe basically threat is
over there you avoid it by moving over
there either way keeping you external to
the truth of he is the one there
plotting for it
and that's the danger of views it always
required external Assumption of external
even the right view for that matter
but the Right View does point back to
itself So eventually you can you can you
can uproot any notion of external
through using that right View
and that's how a lot of hunters have
said before goes beyond the views all
together in other words they're not the
slightest trace of any
like even possibility of assuming
external to the aggregates
assuming Independence in regard to the
aggregates
or assuming like oh you're saying like
health wealth family all of these
assumptions yeah so you start with that
say a person starts with that and then
they inevitably gonna have some coping
mechanism on the mental level and then
and then
you include that as well well the
scoping mechanism
can that be independent of this feeling
of these of these things that are
subjected to change so my coping sense
of safety
well that's another trap that's actually
unsafe so no place to hide
so no place to hide
sorry when the Buddha said um
anybody who believes that they have
health is a fool
you're just or anybody who believes that
um not having health is not a problem is
also for ah fine I'll deal with it
no because they're intoxicated that's a
drunk person doesn't care about the
consequence of his actions because he's
drunk but then when he sobers up he
realized oh my god what have I done
but there is no way of talking that into
him while he's drunk
it doesn't matter
loss of perspective so you realize
that's the pattern I am already in a
state of language perspective
the the being the Health death loss
and you will know that if you simply ask
yourself well can I suffer on account of
anything
can suffer in your eyes on account of
anything that is able to change
or can I not suffer on account of
anything any change
can I remain up in perturbable
composed regardless of how much things
change whether they're dear to me or not
if I lose everything the second would I
be affected or not